Alice Beal Parsons Papers
Alice Beal Parsons Papers
1916-1966
Parsons, Alice Beal, 1886-1962.
12.0 linear ft.
Papers of the American author, novelist, social worker, feminist. Collection includes correspondence (1916-1961), memorabilia, photographs, printed material, published material, and writings (articles, book reviews, drafts of books, typescripts, galley proofs).
149446
Biographical History
Alice Beal Parsons (1886-1962) was an American author, novelist, social worker and feminist.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Alice Beal Parsons Papers consist of correspondence, memorabilia, photographs, printed material, published material, and writings.
Correspondence contains both incoming and outgoing mail, including a typed signed letter from Clarence Darrow.
Memorabilia contains a typescript of a court case in which Mr. Darrow was involved, a typescript of Mrs. Parsons' great-grandmother's journal, and a report card for Laura Parsons.
Photographs contains a small number of personal photographs.
Printed material contains publicity material and radio scripts.
Published material contains clippings concerning Parsons' work as well as a personal biography entitled Forever What We Wish, by Helen Bryant.
Writings contains many of her published articles as well as numerous typescripts of both books and short stories.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is arranged chronologically, as are book reviews in whatever series they appear. All other material is arranged alphabetically.
Related Material
Several articles by Parson are available on the Harper's Magazine website at http://www.harpers.org/subjects/AliceBealParsons.
Subject and Genre Headings
Women Authors; Activism and social reform; Parsons, Alice Beal, 1886-1962.; American literature -- 20th century.; Feminists -- United States.; Women authors, American.; Women novelists, American.; Women social workers -- United States.; Articles.; Autobiographies (literary works); Book reviews.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Drafts (documents); Galley proofs.; Manuscripts for publication.; Photographs.; Authors.; Feminists.; Novelists.; Social workers.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Correspondence, 1916-1961; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 1)
- Memorabilia
  - Transcript: Court case, Illinois vs. Arthur Person, 1920; 7 folders (Box 1)
  - Journal, Lucretia Nevins Starr, 1844-1845; typescript (Box 1)
  - Report card, Laura Parsons (Box 1)
- Photographs
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Printed material
  - Publicity materials (Box 1)
  - Radio scripts (Box 1)
- Published material
  - Book reviews, 1921-1948; 7 folders (Box 1)
  - Book reviews, 1929-1961; 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Book, Forever What We Wish, 1966 (Box 2)
  - Bradford Alumnae Bulletin, 1932 (Box 2)
  - Bretano's Book Parade (Box 2)
  - The Dial, 1929 (Box 2)
  - Dutton Spring Books, 1944 (Box 2)
  - Galleys, Forever What We Wish, 1966 (Box 2)
  - Illinois English Bulletin, 1952 (Box 2)
  - Literary Mideast USA, 1957 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Typescripts, Forever What We Wish, 1966 (Box 2)
  - The Woman Citizen, 1926 (Box 2)
- Writings
  - Articles
    - Beating the economic system, 1931 (Box 2)
    - Certain people of unimportance, 1924 (Box 2)
    - Changing views about the hobo, 1923; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - The conquest of emotion, 1932 (Box 2)
    - The cult of the childless, 1931 (Box 2)
    - The despotism of Polly Ross, 1930; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Evening call, 1940 (Box 2)
    - Every woman's home, 1926 (Box 2)
    - Four ways to support a family: The parents' wages, 1926 (Box 2)
    - The future of marriage, 1931 (Box 2)
    - How changing conditions change mothers, 1926 (Box 2)
    - It's your country -- pitch in, 1945 (Box 2)
    - Legacy of a great lady, 1962 (Box 2)
    - Meantime the summer wind, 1935 (Box 2)
    - Meantime the summer wind, 1953 (Box 2)
    - Midsummer evening, 1935 (Box 2)
    - Sex and genius, 1925; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Should parents tell all?, 1931 (Box 2)
    - Sin, 1923 (Box 3)
    - So you're glad to be home?, 1930 (Box 3)
    - To confess -- or to pretend, 1945 (Box 3)
    - Triumph, 1948 (Box 3)
  - Book review clippings
    - 1921-1949, 6 folders (Box 3)
  - Book reviews
    - 1939-1941, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - 1953 (Box 3)
  - Books
    - The mountain, 1944 (Box 3)
  - Galleys
    - I know what I'd do, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - The mountain, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - The world around the mountain, 4 folders (Box 4)
  - Magazine articles
    - Clippings (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
  - Rough drafts
    - Books
      - Autobiographical, 8 folders (Box 4)
      - Death of a father (Box 4)
      - Fragments, 3 folders (Box 4)
      - The Sandy Point Murders, 3 folders (Box 5)
      - The Sperrys, 5 folders (Box 5)
      - Strangers in Pawlet (Box 5)
      - The traveler, 3 folders (Box 5)
      - The unbelieving sons, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Fragments (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
    - Unfinished novels, 3 folders (Box 5)
    - Unfinished novels, 7 folders (Box 6)
  - Typescripts
    - Books
      - Autobiographical, 3 folders (Box 6)
      - Brothers, 2 folders (Box 6)
      - The children of disobedience, 4 folders (Box 6)
      - Death of a soul, 2 folders (Box 6)
      - Death of a soul, 8 folders (Box 7)
      - The goal, 10 folders (Box 7)
      - The goal (Box 8)
      - Harder to love, 11 folders (Box 8)
      - I know what I'd do, 2 folders (Box 8)
      - The inheritors, 5 folders (Box 8)
      - The inheritors, 5 folders (Box 9)
      - It's a swell town (Box 9)
      - The lost town, 2 folders (Box 9)
      - The man in the mirror, 3 folders (Box 9)
      - Middle west early novel, 2 folders (Box 9)
      - The mountain, 2 folders (Box 9)
      - The Sandy Point murders (Box 9)
      - The second door on the right (Box 9)
      - The second door on the right (Box 10)
      - The second life of Bye Dongan, 4 folders (Box 10)
      - The Sperrys, 2 folders (Box 10)
      - Strangers in Pawlet, 5 folders (Box 10)
      - The turning point, 5 folders (Box 10)
      - The unbelieving sons, 3 folders (Box 10)
      - The wild filly, 2 folders (Box 10)
      - The wild filly, 2 folders (Box 11)
      - Wolf's clothing (Box 11)
      - The world around the mountain, 2 folders (Box 11)
    - Short stories
      - Acl - Mid, 13 folders (Box 11)
      - Mis - Six, 5 folders (Box 12)
      - Sle - Wha, 4 folders (Box 13)
      - Whi - You, 2 folders (Box 14)
      - Untitled (Box 14)